<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: auto-repair | runLevel-6]]></title>
  <link href="http:/runlevel-6.github.io/blog/categories/auto-repair/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http:/runlevel-6.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-01-31T02:16:50-05:00</updated>
  <id>http:/runlevel-6.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ken Zahorec]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Auto Repair: Fixing a leaky door on the 2007 Saab 93]]></title>
    <link href="http:/runlevel-6.github.io/blog/2013/05/04/auto-repair-fixing-a-leaky-door-on-the-2007-saab-93/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-04T01:21:55-04:00</updated>
    <id>http:/runlevel-6.github.io/blog/2013/05/04/auto-repair-fixing-a-leaky-door-on-the-2007-saab-93</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>After a night of heavy rain we have an inch of water in the drivers-side interior footwell!</strong></p>

<p>I am posting this information with hope that it might help others who are experiencing the same problem I had. If you find it of good use, please drop me an email. Please read the disclaimer at the bottom of this document.</p>

<p>The 2007 Saab 93 door leak root cause. A torn foam-panel interior door seal.</p>

<p><img src="/images-saab/5-torn-foam-seal.png" alt="Saab 93" /></p>

<h2>Forward</h2>

<p>In this article we illustrate a solution for a leaking interior door panel on a 2007 Saab 93 2.0t that was discovered in November of 2012.</p>

<h2>Problem described:</h2>

<p>We have had water leaking in on the driver&rsquo;s side for several months, but only after a very heavy rain. On two occasions we had more than an inch of water accumulate!</p>

<h2>Investigation</h2>

<p>I ran a garden hose on the drivers side window for about 2 or 3 minutes and noticed that water was leaking into the interior at the very bottom of the plastic panel attached to the drivers door. The body door seal actually prevents the water from exiting at the bottom of the door opening so it leaks into the cabin and runs onto the carpet into the drivers foot area.</p>

<p>To investigate the root cause, I carefully separated the door panel from the door frame along the lower part of the door. I noticed that the foam seal panel inside the door was damaged, torn up and not connected (adhered to the metal door frame) as it should have been.</p>

<h2>When did the damage occur? At the service dealer 2 years before!</h2>

<p>This got me wondering, since we purchased the car used but still under factory warranty at the time it was purchased. I called the dealer service who confirmed that the car had service performed on the drivers door two years back to replace the window actuator. Apparently the service technician or mechanic, during replacement of the window actuator, had torn up the interior door seal and not bothered to replace or repair it properly. This interior door seal is a thin closed cell foam panel that tears easily when servicing the door mechanics. The panel is adhered to the lower part of the inside of the door and works to keep water moving towards the outside of the door cavity and properly through the drain holes at the bottom of the door.</p>

<p>The attending service manager claimed that the work on the door actuator was guaranteed for 1 year, so the fact that the interior door seal was damaged during that process is past due and there is nothing they can do about it&ndash;even though THEY damaged it in 2010. There was absolutely no way I could tell that the work was substandard without removing the door panel to see it inside the door assembly. So much for professional service and standing by your work. That will be the last time that service dealer gets my business.</p>

<h2>Lesson for service done on a door</h2>

<p>So to make a long story short: If you have ever had work done on the inside of a Saab door, it is imperative that the foam panel seal within the door assembly not be breached. If the seal is not attached properly or is damaged or torn in the repair process you may end up with a door that leaks into the cabin during heavy rains.</p>

<p>Perhaps after service door repairs, a good test at home would be to spray water on the door window for about 15 or 20 minutes to test the seal and make sure the service technician got the seal set up properly. Of course this could be done at the service dealer as part of the repair process to make sure the door handles water properly after service.</p>

<h2>Saab design issue?</h2>

<p>Looking at the Saab door design closely, it is clearly evident that the windows seam at the top of the door is located directly above the lower part of the interior door panel instead of the lower part of the door assembly. This means that any water entering the door-window seam and falling straight down will strike the foam panel and interior parts of the door before finding its way back to the door well drain holes. This particular choice of design makes it imperative that the foam door panel not be breached. I am not sure if this situation occurs in other sporty cars, like the Saab, which tend to have a tapered wider stance at the base of the vehicle when viewed from the front or back of the car. This does help make the car look more appealing and perhaps improves handling by distributing more mass at the base of the car&ndash;a lower center of gravity.</p>

<h2>Repair or replace the part?</h2>

<p>A new foam seal is ~$140 (USD). That is an insane amount of money for a simple piece of foam&ndash;typical service part highway robbery. I will take a stab at fixing it myself. I will use rubberized sealant and transparent box tape. It won&rsquo;t look great, but who cares because the repair work will only be visible if you remove the interior door panel. If I <strong>ever</strong> have to tear out the panel for future repair work on a windows actuator I will consider buying a new foam panel&ndash;but not until then.</p>

<h2>Repairing the foam seal.</h2>

<p>Here are the steps I went through to repair the foam seal in the door. It was very easy and took only a few minutes&hellip;</p>

<p>First we heat the door handle with a hair dryer. We want to get the plastic hot so it can flex more easily.</p>

<p><img src="/images-saab/1-heating-door-handle.png" alt="heating up the door handle" /></p>

<p>After the door handle has been warmed up, we can gently pull and easily snap off the plastic door handle cover.</p>

<p><img src="/images-saab/2-door-handle-cover-removed.png" alt="door handle plastic cover removed" /></p>

<p>Now we must remove two torx bolts which hold the door handle to the door frame.</p>

<p><img src="/images-saab/3-star-driver-upper-handle.png" alt="door panel upper torx" /></p>

<p><img src="/images-saab/4-star-driver-lower-handle.png" alt="door panel lower torx" /></p>

<p>We then gently snap the door panel away and lift it gently to detach it from the door frame. We must be careful with the plastic snaps. The door panel remains loosely attached near the door lever. We can now inspect the the torn foam door seal.</p>

<p><img src="/images-saab/5-torn-foam-seal.png" alt="torn interior door seal" /></p>

<p>Lifting the lower section of the torn foam seal exposes the interior cavity of the door. This is where the water is coming from. The water runs along the torn foam panel and drops onto the interior door panel. From there it enters the cabin.</p>

<p><img src="/images-saab/6-leak-point.png" alt="inner door cavity exposed" /></p>

<p>We carefully use the rubberized sealant to repair the tear in the foam seal. We add quality transparent box tape to further mend any tears and spread the sealant across the tearing. It does not look like new, but it works just fine. The unsightly repair work will be covered completely when the interior door panel is snapped back into position.</p>

<p><img src="/images-saab/7-repaired-foam-seal.png" alt="repaired door seal" /></p>

<p>Afterwards, a lengthy garden hose test reveals that the repair work did the job! The door no longer leaks into the interior of the cabin.</p>

<h2>Summary</h2>

<p>We successfully repaired the leaking door on the 2007 Saab 93 2.0t. The work took about one hour and we spent about $5. We saved at least $140 in the process and learned a few things along the way. All in all it was a big win-win. <strong>That is $5 and one hour of fussing around!</strong></p>

<p>The solution has worked flawlessly for 18 months, including winter and now several torrential spring rains. We still have the option to replace the foam seal whenever we want to endure the $140 cost. I might consider, instead of cheap flimsy foam, using a custom fit piece of durable 4 or 6 mil plastic visquene.</p>

<p>If we had the service dealer fix it, we would have spent $140 for the part, and at least $90 for the labor. On top of that we would had to drive to the service dealer twice resulting in 2 hours of travel time&ndash;the dealer is 30 minutes away from my home. <strong>That is $230 and 2 hours of our time and travel costs.</strong></p>

<h3>Disclaimer:</h3>

<p>The information provided here is not a suggestion or endorsement that anyone should attempt to perform the activities shown or described. This information is provided as-is to show how I solved the problem described. Any repairs you make to your car, or someone else&rsquo;s car, are done at your own risk. The author assumes no responsibility or liability for the actions of others or the results obtained or problems encountered, including loss of any kind, from use of the information on this site.</p>

<p>In other words; You better know what you are doing before trying your own repair work. If you are unsure as to what you are doing, then seek out a qualified mechanic to perform the work.</p>

<p><a href='#TOP'><img alt="back to top of page" style="border-width:0" src="http:/runlevel-6.github.io/images/nav-to-top_80x23.png" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Auto Headlight Repair: Cleaning cloudy headlamp lenses to look like new again]]></title>
    <link href="http:/runlevel-6.github.io/blog/2013/04/21/auto-headlight-repair-cleaning-cloudy-headlamp-lenses-to-look-like-new-again/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-21T00:45:35-04:00</updated>
    <id>http:/runlevel-6.github.io/blog/2013/04/21/auto-headlight-repair-cleaning-cloudy-headlamp-lenses-to-look-like-new-again</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Driving down the street at night and wondering why I can&rsquo;t see the road the way I used to be able to. Are my headlamps on?</strong></p>

<p>I am posting this information with hope that it might help others who are experiencing the same problem I had. If you find it of good use, please drop me an email to let me know. Please read the disclaimer at the bottom of this document.</p>

<p>Does your headlamp lens look cloudy and dull&ndash;like this one? :)
<img src="/images-headlamp-lens/celica-lens-cloudy_400x267.png" alt="cloudy headlamp lens" /></p>

<h2>Forward</h2>

<p>In this article we illustrate a solution for the embedded dirt, grime, and chemical residue, that builds up on the surface of the acrylic headlamp lens.</p>

<h2>Problem described:</h2>

<p>The headlamp lens on my daughters 2000 Celica GTS has been looking very cloud for a few years now. It has become rather frustrating because it interfers with the performance of the headlamps on the car. The headlamp system on the Celica is top-notch when it is working properly. The problem is that the clouded headlamp diffuses the light and reduces the illuminating distance of the headlamp system&ndash;this impedes night driving and can be unsafe. It is also very frustrating to look at after cleaning and waxing the otherwise great looking car. It stands out like a black eye on the poor little Celica&ndash;we gotta fix it. :(</p>

<p>Upon close inspection, it appears the the clouding of the lens is mostly, if not entirely, on the outside surface of the lens.</p>

<h2>Possible solutions:</h2>

<p>The guy at AutoZone suggested to my daughter that she try a lens repair kit. The kit is from Turtle Wax, and is called &ldquo;Headlight Lens Restorer&rdquo;. It costs about $10.00. She came to visit this weekend and brought the kit with her. We decided to give it a try. I must say I was a little skeptical at first, but afterwards I was totally blown away by the results.</p>

<h2>Repairing the lens</h2>

<p>Here are the steps we went through to restore the headlight lenses, both of them, on the Celica. It was very easy and took only a few minutes&hellip;</p>

<p>Below is the Turtle Wax kit my daughter brought home from AutoZone.</p>

<p><img src="/images-headlamp-lens/turtle-wax-lens-repair-kit_400x514.png" alt="2000 Celica GTS rear view" /></p>

<p>Below is a shot of the Celica GTS, looking just great from the rear.</p>

<p><img src="/images-headlamp-lens/celica-gts-2000_400x250.png" alt="2000 Celica GTS rear view" /></p>

<p>But low and behold, the view from the front shows the ugly, dull, headlamp on the passenger side.</p>

<p><a href="/images-headlamp-lens/celica-lens-cloudy_400x267.png">cloudy headlamp lens</a></p>

<p>Following the instructions, we tape off the body surrounding the headlamp to prevent any damage to the paint on the vehicle.</p>

<p><img src="/images-headlamp-lens/taped-celica-lens_400x247.png" alt="tape off the lens" /></p>

<p>Following the instructions, and using an old towel, we first try to use the white polishing agent provided in the kit. With just a bit of polishing effort, the grime embedded into the lens surface starts to immediately show up on the towel&ndash;wow great!</p>

<p><img src="/images-headlamp-lens/apply-polishing-agent_400x298.png" alt="applying headlight lens polishing agent" /></p>

<p>Afterwards we applied the acrylic sealer provided in the kit using the small application cloth provided. The headlamp lens looks like new again. It was simply a remarkable transformation&ndash;like NEW again! Crystal CLEAR! It has not looked this great since we purchased the car. My daugher and I are both <strong>amazed</strong> at the results!</p>

<p><img src="/images-headlamp-lens/lens-looking-great_400x302.png" alt="clear headlamp lens" /></p>

<p>&hellip;and now we have a great looking front view of the Celca GTS!</p>

<p><img src="/images-headlamp-lens/celica-front-repaired-lens_400x269.png" alt="2000 Celica GTS front view" /></p>

<h2>Summary</h2>

<p>Although the kit came with some additional products for sanding out and refinishing the headlamp lens, the only parts of the kit we used was the white polishing and cleaning agent and the acrylic sealant towelette. I highly recomment this product. It is well worth $10.00.</p>

<p>BTW&ndash;A single new headlamp lens for the 2000 Celica GTS will run you about $270 from the dealer.</p>

<h3>Disclaimer:</h3>

<p>The information provided here is not a suggestion or endorsement that anyone should attempt to perform the activities shown or described. This information is provided as-is to show how I solved the problem described. Any repairs you make to your car, or someone else&rsquo;s car, are done at your own risk. The author assumes no responsibility or liability for the actions of others or the results obtained or problems encountered, including loss of any kind, from use of the information on this site.</p>

<p>In other words; You better know what you are doing before trying your own repair work. If you are unsure as to what you are doing, then seek out a qualified mechanic to perform the work.</p>

<p><a href='#TOP'><img alt="back to top of page" style="border-width:0" src="http:/runlevel-6.github.io/images/nav-to-top_80x23.png" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Auto Repair: Fixing the BMW 325 faulty rear tail light]]></title>
    <link href="http:/runlevel-6.github.io/blog/2013/04/04/auto-repair-fixing-the-bmw-325-faulty-rear-tail-light/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-04T23:49:08-04:00</updated>
    <id>http:/runlevel-6.github.io/blog/2013/04/04/auto-repair-fixing-the-bmw-325-faulty-rear-tail-light</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I am posting this information with hope that it might help others who are experiencing the same problem I am having with the E46 tail light assembly. If you find it of good use, please drop me an email to let me know. Please read the disclaimer at the bottom of this document.</p>

<p>Can you spot the problem in this rear tail light connector?</p>

<p><img src="/images-e46/show_bad_lead_400x300.jpg" alt="rear light assembly" /></p>

<h3>Forward</h3>

<p>My 18 year old son has been having problems with his 2001 BMW 325i. The body style is E46. The right tail light is not working properly. It is blinking too fast and does not seem to have enough illumination. It recently stopped working at all. I told him not to drive it until we had it repaired, so of course he has been quite anxious to get back to driving his car—he loves his BMW. He has been avoiding driving the “spare” family van, a rusty 94 Mercury Villager with a broken heater, broken AC, and 198,000 miles on it—can you blame him? Always up for a challenge and also for saving a buck or two, I decided to take a crack at fixing the BMW&hellip; :)</p>

<h3>Problem described:</h3>

<p>The right rear directional indicator, or turn signal, is very dim and flashes too quickly. Other lights within the same assembly are also very dim. The car keeps indicating a directional light warning on the dash panel. This problem went on for a couple of weeks and now, as of very recently, it has stopped working completely.</p>

<h3>Possible solutions:</h3>

<p>My first thought was that the problem might be with the light bulbs, so they were all checked and were found to be working perfectly. Next thought was that the problem could be a blown fuse. We checked the fuses, and they were ok as well. I started looking into replacement of the relay mechanism. The relay seems to be difficult to get to, so I went to the web for some information.</p>

<p>While searching around for information on the relay I was able to find out that there is a <a href="http://forum.e46fanatics.com/showthread.php?t=533309&amp;highlight=melted+tail+light">documented problem</a> in the way the light assembly has been designed for this car. Although I am grateful for the author&rsquo;s post on this, I believe this solution looks far more complicated than it needs to be. I solved it instead using one single wire connection back into the BMW 325i E46 wire harness.</p>

<p>The design problem appears to be in the material BMW chose for the ground return circuit in the tail light assembly, stamped steel sheathing. This material can not handle the ground return current. It basically gets too hot and eventually fries out at the thinnest point (least conductive) which happens to be within the connector contact area. I would not be suprised to find out that other BMW body styles have the same problem assuming that the folks at BMW might be using similar material selections on other vehicles.</p>

<h3>Problem solved:</h3>

<p>The solution I chose was to remove the ground return path from the connector and provide a much more conductive path using an external piece of 12 gauge stranded copper wire pulled from an old AC cord. Nothing beats copper wire for moving electrons. Ok, perhaps a super-conductor, but we aren&rsquo;t going there today :)</p>

<p>The repair job took me about 40 minutes or so to complete&ndash;it took me far longer to write this article. The lights on the vehicle are now working perfectly!</p>

<h3>Step by step what I did to solve the problem:</h3>

<p>Below is a view of the 2001 BMW 325i E46 rear light assembly, once it has been removed from the trunk area.</p>

<p><img src="/images-e46/e46_right_rear_light_assembly_400x300.jpg" alt="rear light assembly" /></p>

<p>Notice the burnt-out conductor below. The third conductor from the right of the connector. It has basically melted and corroded away from the intense heat. &ndash;very poor choice of material in this case—shame on BMW for that one.</p>

<p><img src="/images-e46/show_bad_lead_400x300.jpg" alt="rear light assembly" /></p>

<p>Below I have cut the bad conductor from the assembly using a pair of snub-nose wire clippers. You don&rsquo;t want to leave the old unattached conductor in the assembly, it could short out one of the other conductors if it came loose.</p>

<p><img src="/images-e46/cut_bad_lead_400x300.jpg" alt="rear light assembly" /></p>

<p>Below I have removed the bad conductor from the connector assembly. I just pull it out from the bottom using a pair of needle-nose pliers. Notice also that I have raised and clipped the strip at the thicker area to ready it for a new slide-on connector&hellip;</p>

<p><img src="/images-e46/removed_lead_400x300.jpg" alt="rear light assembly" /></p>

<p>You will need some tooling for performing electircal crimping. This is very inexepensive equipment and can be found at your local hardware, electrical, or builders supply store, such as Lowes or Home Depot. I just happen to have this stuff in my repair box for situations like this. Below is a picture of the tooling I used for this job. There is also DELL laptop with mouse in the picture, but you won&rsquo;t need either of those for this job. :)</p>

<p><img src="/images-e46/termination-kit_400x533.jpg" alt="rear light assembly" /></p>

<p>Below I have used the crimping tool and a blue slide-on connector to attached a new ground lead to the thicker, more conductive part of the metal strip. The unit is now ready to take back and install into the vehicle. If you do this you must make sure that the wire you pick is of greater current carrying capacity than what is found in the wiring harness in the car. In my case I used 12 gauge stranded copper wire which is a considerable improvement in conductivity than to what BMW is using in the wire harness. 14 gauge stranded copper would be great also. I would not go any smaller than 14 gauge. This piece of 12 gauge was cut and pulled from an old extension cord lying around the house.</p>

<p><img src="/images-e46/lead_attached_400x300.jpg" alt="rear light assembly" /></p>

<p>Now we are ready to install the light assembly unit back into the vehicle. Make sure all of the bulbs are inserted back into the assembly and take it back to the trunk of the vehicle.</p>

<p>Below is the unit sitting in the trunk and connected to the wire-harness. You&rsquo;ll have to excuse the visible junk in the trunk—my son is not very particular about his car trunk. As you can see, I have clipped the brown ground lead from the vehicle&rsquo;s wire harness and connected my green ground wire to it using another blue crimping connector from the connector set above. The crimp tooling and connectors are great to work with; Simple to use, effective, and quick!</p>

<p><img src="/images-e46/connection_complete_400x300.jpg" alt="rear light assembly" /></p>

<p>Next we snapped the light assembly back into position within the trunk and checked out the lights. Hooray! Everything is now working perfectly. Lights are as bright and snappy as the day the vehicle was purchased. The light warning is no longer appearing at the dash board. My son can now drive his car again! He&rsquo;s a happy camper and we are not out the $ hundreds it would have probably cost us to deal with the BMW service center.</p>

<p>&hellip;As a precautionary measure I checked the left rear light assembly for the same problem. The materials and connectors are the same on the left side, but I did not see any sign of a problem on that side. For now, I decided to leave the left side alone. Perhaps we&rsquo;ll be dealing with the left side in the future. :)</p>

<p>A few other things we have done at home with this BMW 325i E46 since we purchased it as a used vehicle a few years back:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Changed break shoes and brake wear sensors front and back—pretty easy task and saved us a bundle.</p></li>
<li><p>Performed regular oil and filter change.</p></li>
<li><p>Fixed a leaking O-ring on the top radiator hose.</p></li>
<li><p>Changed serpentine belt on front of the engine—that one was fun—NOT!</p></li>
<li><p>Front end alignment—yes we can do that also without the use of any expensive equipment!</p></li>
<li><p>Changed the rear drivers-side window drive motor.</p></li>
</ol>


<h3>Disclaimer:</h3>

<p>The information provided here is not a suggestion or endorsement that anyone should attempt to perform the activities shown or described. This information is provided as-is to show how I solved the problem described. Any repairs you make are done at your own risk. The author assumes no responsibility or liability for the actions of others or the results obtained or problems encountered, including loss of any kind, from use of the information on this site.</p>

<p>In other words; You better know what you are doing before trying your own repair work. If you are unsure as to what you are doing, then seek out a qualified mechanic to perform the work.</p>

<p><a href='#TOP'><img alt="back to top of page" style="border-width:0" src="images/nav-to-top_80x23.png" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
