<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: electrical | RunLevel-6]]></title>
  <link href="http://runlevel-6.github.io/runlevel-6/blog/categories/electrical/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://runlevel-6.github.io/runlevel-6/"/>
  <updated>2015-01-04T23:52:39-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://runlevel-6.github.io/runlevel-6/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ken Zahorec]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Basement Upgrade: Creating the new hangout...]]></title>
    <link href="http://runlevel-6.github.io/runlevel-6/blog/2013/04/30/basement-upgrade-creating-the-new-hangout/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-30T10:45:07-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://runlevel-6.github.io/runlevel-6/blog/2013/04/30/basement-upgrade-creating-the-new-hangout</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My wife and I had been living in our home, with children, for a number of years and decided it was time for general improvement of the basement. The basement was basically roughed-in but nothing was done beyond what was required for the basic requirements to satisfy the building code. It was not a living area for our home and we wanted to create a living area for our family to enjoy.</p>

<h3>Experience</h3>

<p>After much careful thought, I decided to proceed with the project on my own. I had some home construction experience, from many years back, working with my dad as part of his construction company, Equity Builders, in Lorain, Ohio. My father was an exceptional carpenter and I gained a great appreciation of carpentry and general contracting working with him. I also have an undergraduate degree in electrical engineering&ndash;so the electrical elements of the project came along reasonably easily for me as did the general construction. I did have to do some research on building and electrical codes to make sure everything I was doing would be within the limits of building codes in my area.</p>

<p>The advantages of DIY include:</p>

<ul>
<li>Saving a considerable amount of money</li>
<li>Ability to provide a great job for my two sons to learn and earn money.</li>
<li>Everyone learning lots of new concepts and skills</li>
<li>Remaining in complete control of the job along the way</li>
</ul>


<p>The disadvantages of DIY:</p>

<ul>
<li>Taking more time to complete the project</li>
<li>Spending a few hundred, or so, hours of my time in the basement instead of doing other things</li>
</ul>


<h3>Warning&hellip;</h3>

<p>If you decide to try a basement improvement project on your own make sure you do enough research to understand what you are getting into. Find some experienced people to talk with about the project if you do not have enough experience yourself. Plan the project in phases and celebrate the completion of each phase. If you are unsure about anything you are doing, then get some help. It can be very costly to have to tear something apart because it was not built properly. There are also many dangers that you will encounter in the building process&ndash;power tools, adhesives, paints, electrical distribution components, etc.. The risk of getting seriously hurt goes up dramatically if you don&rsquo;t know what you are doing. Most importantly you want to end up with a safe living environment when you are done&ndash;so pay close attention to building, electrical, and plumbing codes&ndash;think seriously about these and don&rsquo;t be afraid to spend some extra money to make sure the new living environment is safe.</p>

<p>If you do not have experience consider doing some smaller jobs first, then gradually working your way up. Perhaps even helping a professional complete a job, as a part time learning experice. You can offer your help for less, as a means to gain valuable part time on-the-job experience.</p>

<h3>Site Considerations</h3>

<p>When we had our home built, we specified deeper 13 course block basement with the thought that we might eventually improve the basement into a living area. The distance from basement floor to upper level exposed floor joists is about 8 &frac12; feet. Having the deeper basement allowed enough room to build soffits and ceiling into the basement yet provide for a generous amount of head room. The cost of the additional row of block for the basement, at the time the home was built, was around $400&ndash;a worthwhile investment. The basement has a generous amount of open floor space free from utilites above it. It is very dry and we have never had any water issues. The home is built on one of the higher level lots in the development.</p>

<h3>Getting Started</h3>

<p>To get the plan started I created a drawing using a CAD tool. I picked an open source tool called LibreCAD to do the drawing. I spent several weeks just drawing, correcting, sketching, and planning what improvements would be made and how to accomplish the task. My original drawings had a small kitchen included, but that was scaled back because of space and cost concerns. Once we had an aggreable plan, I procrastinated for a few months, then began doing the work. I have done most everything so far, with some occasional help from a few of my friends on some of the larger and/or heavier tasks&ndash;such as the drywall finishing. I also had my 15 year old son help me, who learned many skills while doing so. I learned quite a bit also, and continue to learn as I work to complete the project. My older son is also helping me now, when he can, and is also learning much about building.</p>

<h3>Proceeding to build</h3>

<p>With the improvement plan drawing complete, we now have the confidence needed to move forward. We are now in the build phase of the project. We are working the project in phases and decided to leave the last phase, the bathroom, for a later time&ndash;much later. Work has not been moving as quickly as I originally expected but we are making steady progress&ndash;it is a rather large project for one person. It has become a regular part-time weekend job. I am doing most of the work on my own with some help occasionally from my two sons.</p>

<p>Below is the framing work for the first build which divided the basement into entertainment and utility space.</p>

<p><img src="/images-basement/IMG_2243_400x267.png" alt="furnace room" /></p>

<p>The plan calls for more electrical capacity in the basement&ndash;a lot more. The main panel is nearly out of slots. Here I have added a side-car distribution panel for the finished side of the basement. It will carry the 240V baseboard heater load, wall outlets, and light utilities for the finished side of the basement.</p>

<p><img src="/images-basement/distribution-side-car_400x267.png" alt="furnace room" /></p>

<p>The side-car distribution is operational. I have a bit more work to do on it. I still need to tie the romex down with some staples and complete the layout document sheet on the inside of the door.</p>

<p><img src="/images-basement/distribution-side-car-2_400x267.png" alt="furnace room" /></p>

<p><img src="/images-basement/distribution-side-car-3_400x267.png" alt="furnace room" /></p>

<p>Here we have our friendly home electrician&ndash;me. The switches in the 4 gang electrical workbox all operate perfectly. A happy camper indeed&hellip;</p>

<p><img src="/images-basement/IMG_2259_400x600.png" alt="electrical" /></p>

<p>With the electrical rough in complete, we can begin to mud, sand smooth, and then prime-coat the walls. Dry wall and finishing is labor intensive and very messy. This was about as big of a drywall job as I could put up with and I got some help on the finishing work from my brother in law. The job seemed to take forever and was very messy.</p>

<p><img src="/images-basement/IMG_2380_400x267.png" alt="finishing walls" /></p>

<p><img src="/images-basement/IMG_2379_400x267.png" alt="finishing walls" /></p>

<p>Here you can see the positioning of the recessed lights on the finished side of the basement. Note the mason string line used as a guide to position the lights in two parallel lines across the basement. If you want a straight line, use a very taught string.</p>

<p><img src="/images-basement/recessed-lights-layout_400x267.png" alt="positioning recessed lights" /></p>

<p>On to the prime coat and finish woodwork. We still have a few places on the walls that need a bit more more attention. I am waiting to do the final touchups until all the woodwork is complete. I found that the installation process for the finish woodworking occasionally tends to ding up the walls here and there. One final fresh coat of paint near the end of the project should take care of everything.</p>

<p><img src="/images-basement/IMG_4437_400x267.png" alt="finishing walls" /></p>

<p><img src="/images-basement/IMG_4438_400x267.png" alt="finishing walls" /></p>

<p>Here we are now below, into the second build which adds a central soffit to cover the overhead beam and air ducts and finished walls to cover most of the foundation. The second build will complete the division of the basement with an addition of another internal partition with a doorway. The goal for the second build is to complete the living area ceiling, walls, and woodwork&ndash;bringing it into full completion except for the floor. Part of this second build is now complete with woodwork and finish work complete. Note the recessed ceiling lights.</p>

<p><img src="/images-basement/IMG_2970_400x267.png" alt="furnace room" /></p>

<p>Now we move on to finishing the ugly support posts. We use a combination of a level and a keen line-of-sight to make sure the support posts are aligned with each other and plumb before we start&ndash;they are. I cut some 2x4s to length and run a shallow angled groove down the center. I use two heavy U-bolts on each post to clamp a 2x4 onto the post&ndash;then apply adhesive. We take special care to use only straight 2x4s, and align their surface at the proper position on the post to be parallel with the room wall. This provides a rock-solid and truly aligned nailing surface for the first piece of poplar 1x8 woodwork which is glued and nailed onto the 2x4. We make sure to use a level to plumb the first poplar 1x8 for a good start on each post.</p>

<p><img src="/images-basement/post-finishing-1_400x267.png" alt="post finishing 1" /></p>

<p>With the first piece nailed and glued directly to the 2x4, we now work our way around the post, nailing each edge of the 1x8 poplar to the edge of the previous piece with a 15 gauge nail gun&hellip;</p>

<p><img src="/images-basement/post-finishing-2_400x267.png" alt="post finishing 2" /></p>

<p><img src="/images-basement/post-finishing-3_400x267.png" alt="post finishing 3" /></p>

<p>Afterwards, we fill nail holes using Minwax Woodfiller, then using a sandpaper stapled to a large wood-block - a sanding block. We sand all of the surfaces first with course, then with fine sandpaper. It takes lots of sanding to get it just right. We dont want to see any machine marks or feel any mis-aligned joints. The finished product is worth the effort. We still have trim to complete at the top and bottom of the posts and will get to that after the ceiling is complete.</p>

<p>The posts are looking great so far and you can also see how the central soffit finished out. The paired electrical workboxes in the soffit are one for electrical supply and another for DMX computer light interface&ndash;added to the project for fun and entertainment&ndash;this place is eventually going to rock!</p>

<p><img src="/images-basement/post-finishing-4_400x267.png" alt="post finishing 4" /></p>

<p>We are now getting ready to apply the ceiling material on the uppermost ceiling surface at the floor joists, which will be a tongue-and-groove solid wood SPF siding product. The ceiling material will be nailed to a sub-ceiling that we build out using 1.5&#8221; x 0.75&#8221; firring strips. Below we are using a laser level&ndash;my friend Rich loaned it to me. The masking tape markers are carefully stuck in place, using the laser level, to the desired position for the sub-ceiling&ndash;very close to the the floor joists. The folded tape ends provide a perfectly flat guide for the sub-ceiling nailers which will be glued and nailed to the level of tape markers.</p>

<p>Trying to forgo the firring strips and nail the ceiling directly to the floor joists would create far too much height variation in the finished ceiling because the bottoms of the floor joists are not leveled perfectly with each other. Floor joists tend to be crowned and flat to various degrees. Their with can vary in some cases. Loading on the upper deck can cause some variations as well. The firring strips make it all come out perfectly flat.</p>

<p><img src="/images-basement/laser-level_400x267.png" alt="laser level" /></p>

<p>Here the sub-ceiling nailers are going into place at the exact position the masking tape markers were hung. This effectively flattens the ceiling in preparation for the finished product. The clamp was used as a helping hand to hold up the nailer while it is being positioned and nailed.</p>

<p><img src="/images-basement/ceiling-leveling_400x267.png" alt="sub-ceiling with recessed light" /></p>

<p>I like to keep the tools together and organized. This helps prevent me from spending too much time in search of tools that were left laying around.</p>

<p><img src="/images-basement/tools-1_400x323.png" alt="sub-ceiling with recessed light" /></p>

<p>Using a 15 gauge nail gun really saves time. You can see how the clamp is used to make handling and aligning the material much easer while nailing it.</p>

<p><img src="/images-basement/nailing-subceiling_400x325.png" alt="sub-ceiling nailing gun" /></p>

<p>More sub-ceiling nailers going into place. The entire sub-ceiling is coming out perfectly flat&ndash;just what we need.</p>

<p><img src="/images-basement/ceiling-leveling-2_400x267.png" alt="sub-ceiling progress" /></p>

<p>We use a string to mark and position the first piece of ceiling material. A tight string does not lie&ndash;it gives you a perfectly straigt line to work from.</p>

<p><img src="/images-basement/string-layout-1_400x267.png" alt="sub-ceiling progress" /></p>

<p>We transfer the line produced by the string onto the subceiling nailers. This line markes the position for the first piece of &frac34; inch ceiling material. We want to get a perfectly aligned and straight start&ndash;to which the remaining material will be aligned to. We could have used a chalk line but I didn&rsquo;t want to bother with blue chalk dust cleanup afterwards.</p>

<p><img src="/images-basement/string-layout-2_400x267.png" alt="sub-ceiling progress" /></p>

<p>Here is the start on the ceiling for one section of the basement. The material is nailed using 2 inch 15 gauge nails driven from a Senco nail gun. First piece is spot glued and nailed on both edges of the material&ndash;we want a good foundation piece that will not move. The second and remaining &frac34; inch SPF material is spot glued and nailed at the leading edge, just behind the tongue, to the sub-ceiling nailers. The job is rather cumbersome and requires two people to position, hold, and nail each piece into place. The ceiling is extremely solid&ndash;you can bounce a basketball against it. It adds to the stiffness and structure of the flooring system directly above it.</p>

<p><img src="/images-basement/ceiling-finish-start_400x300.png" alt="sub-ceiling progress" /></p>

<p>The natural wood is really looking great so far. The edges will be eventually be finished out with crown molding, nail holes filled, and a final coat of finish will be applied to the entire ceiling. This is the small section of basement ceiling. On the other side of the soffit the ceiling area is at least 3 times the size of this one. &hellip;we still have lots of ceiling work to do.</p>

<p><img src="/images-basement/ceiling_400x267.png" alt="upper ceiling and soffit" /></p>

<p>Getting back to working on the ceiling I find that I am working mainly on my own. I decided to make a set of support brackets to help install the ceiling material on the larger side of the basement. I need something to hold the material in place with enough force so that it will stay in place and allow me to adjust it before nailing it. What I learned from working on the smaller side is that it is very difficult to hold the first piece and others in place before nailing them. These brackets below will allow me to position and secure the piece before nailing it. I took some quick measurements and spent 30 minutes or so making these from scrap material. The bracket is designed to slide along the sub-ceiling nailers.</p>

<p><img src="/images-basement/support-bracket-1_400x383.png" alt="upper ceiling and soffit" /></p>

<p><img src="/images-basement/support-bracket-2_400x460.png" alt="upper ceiling and soffit" /></p>

<p>You can see how the foam wedge provides enough force to hold the material firmly against the ceiling. This is great. It allows me to carfully align the material before nailing it. I am just getting started on the first row of material on the larger section of ceiling.</p>

<p><img src="/images-basement/support-bracket-use-1_400x267.png" alt="upper ceiling and soffit" /></p>

<p><img src="/images-basement/support-bracket-use-2_400x254.png" alt="upper ceiling and soffit" /></p>

<p>All of the end cuts are made on a compound miter saw. I really like the DeWalt&ndash;it is easy to use and cuts perfectly.</p>

<p><img src="/images-basement/saw-crosscut-1_400x267.png" alt="upper ceiling and soffit" /></p>

<p>I have the saw set to undercut each piece by a few degrees. This helps prevent visual gaps when butted to another piece of material.</p>

<p><img src="/images-basement/saw-overcut_4639_400x267.png" alt="upper ceiling and soffit" /></p>

<p>The first row of material has been spot-glued and nailed in place. It is looking as straight as the string we used earlier to mark the position. Using the support-brackets made a big difference in the amount of effort. It takes me far less effort now, working alone, than it did earlier with two people trying to align and muscle the material around without the bracket.</p>

<p><img src="/images-basement/first-run-west-side-1_400x267.png" alt="upper ceiling and soffit" /></p>

<p>After completing the open ceilings, we will be adding crown molding and finishing out the woodwork down the walls and at the floor base. Although we still have lots of work to do to complete the second build, the basement living area is starting to look like a great place to hang out.</p>

<p>Stay tuned for more as we complete the project&hellip;</p>

<p>document date: 2013-04-30</p>

<p><a href='#TOP'><img alt="back to top of page" style="border-width:0" src="http://runlevel-6.github.io/runlevel-6/images/nav-to-top_80x23.png" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Electric Range Repair: Can I do it myself?]]></title>
    <link href="http://runlevel-6.github.io/runlevel-6/blog/2013/04/21/electric-range-repair-can-i-do-it-myself/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-21T04:05:53-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://runlevel-6.github.io/runlevel-6/blog/2013/04/21/electric-range-repair-can-i-do-it-myself</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I am posting this information with hope that it might help others who are experiencing the same problem. If you find it of good use, please drop me an email to let me know. Please read the disclaimer at the bottom of this document.</p>

<p>Below is a range which has two top burners no longer working. It is currently a two-burner range. We need to fix it.</p>

<p><img src="/images-range/range-1_400x393.png" alt="range front top view" /></p>

<h2>Forward</h2>

<p>Two of the top burners on our home Frigidaire range stopped working over the past year. The range has been in service for 12 years. The center section of the right-front dual element burner and the front section of the dual burner left-side element no longer work. With both burners out, the range has become frustrating to use with only two functional elements&ndash;three if you count the warming element. I need to do something about it.</p>

<h2>Options to consider</h2>

<p>After some investigation on the Internet the best prices I could find was $200 for the left side burner and $113 for the large right-front burner. What gives with those prices? That&rsquo;s $313 plus $7 shipping for what amounts to parts that look like they cost less than $10 each to manufacture. These things should not cost more than a simple toaster&ndash;about $20 each. I can buy a brand new electric range for less than $500! Why are these parts so expensive? There is simply no way I would spend that much on a 12 year old range! It will get replaced with a new unit if I can&rsquo;t fix it here and now with my own tools&hellip;</p>

<h2>The decision</h2>

<p>With nothing really to lose with this range, I decide to try to take a rather <strong>unconventional approach</strong> and repair the range elements <strong>by hand</strong>. If I could pull this off, it will save us from having to replace the range, which would be about $500 - $700. I decide at this point that I will never buy a glass-top range again and it will not be a Frigidaire. I have been thoroughly dissapointed with all of our Frigidaire appliances, including this range.</p>

<h2>Warning</h2>

<p>If you decide to try repairing a range based on the information at this site or any other information, then you had better know what you are doing. Most importantly, make sure the range is unplugged before, and while, attempting to perform any work on it. Read the disclaimer at the end of this page.</p>

<h2>Proceeding with the repair work&hellip;</h2>

<p>Below are the tools and materials I used for the job. Note the connector kit, in the blue container, which was purchased a few years back at the local hardware store. One of the wooden firring strips will be used to hold up the rangetop.</p>

<p><img src="/images-range/range-24_400x250.png" alt="tools used to repair range" /></p>

<p>Below is the range which I have already removed from the counter area. It is inplugged and ready to be diagnosed. The remaining pictures tell the story from start to finish.</p>

<p><img src="/images-range/range-2_400x194.png" alt="front view of range" /></p>

<p>Below I have removed the four mounting scews at the side of the range top and have supported, from the back, the rangetop. This is a view from the rear of the range. I had someone hold the rangetop secure while working on it. There is no hinge at the front to prevent it from sliding out of place and falling&ndash;which almost happened to me. Securing it temporarily at the front with duct tape might also have been a good approach.</p>

<p><img src="/images-range/range-3_400x307.png" alt="range top lifted with support" /></p>

<p>Below is right-front burner element, fully exposed and ready for diagnosis.</p>

<p><img src="/images-range/range-4_400x261.png" alt="range right-front heat element" /></p>

<p>Below is a multi-meter which I will be using as a simple continuity tester to try to determine if and where a break in the heating element might be located.</p>

<p><img src="/images-range/range-5_400x267.png" alt="electronic multi-meter" /> |</p>

<p>I spent three minutes, or so, testing the continuity on portions of the heating element until I located a break point in the element&hellip;</p>

<p><img src="/images-range/range-6_400x267.png" alt="testing heating element for fault" /></p>

<p>The red circle shows the break point in the heating element. It is the common conductor element for the small center portion of the element. I lifted it slightly from the coil to better illustrate it.</p>

<p><img src="/images-range/range-7-marked_400x267.png" alt="fault identified" /></p>

<p>In the next few picures, I fabricate a small specialized crimping connector from a standard aluminum alloy connector in the kit. I will use it to mend the break in the heating element.</p>

<p><img src="/images-range/range-8_400x273.png" alt="connector" /></p>

<p><img src="/images-range/range-9_400x287.png" alt="connector bent" /></p>

<p><img src="/images-range/range-10_400x238.png" alt="connector bent and clipped" /></p>

<p>Here below, the crimping connector has been crimped to the element to re-join the broken element along the nearby element for the other section of the burner. The crimp was done using the large needle-nose pliers in the parts picture earlier above.</p>

<p><img src="/images-range/range-11_400x252.png" alt="heat element repaired" /></p>

<p>After an initial test of the element, we discovered a bright <strong>hot spot</strong> on the element just before the mending point. This was a thermal stress point because a very small section of the element wire was carrying current for both coils of the burner. This would, for sure, be a future fail point of the element if left as was. I did not include a picture of the hot spot at the mending point&ndash;I was focusing on an accomodating solution and forgot to take one.</p>

<p>The hot spot was a problem. I had to find a way to improve the conductivity along this section of element wire.  To fix the hot spot; I carefully fabricated a much larger crimping part, using a much larger standard connector from the kit. I made sure to have the larger part crimp over the smaller part and also crimp the larger connector directly onto the heavy contact point passing through the edge of the element. I had to lift the insulation just a bit to make the connection to the edge of the element. This new crimp part provided the added conductivity needed to prevent the bright hot spot at the mended point. The heavy aluminum has far less resistance than the resistive heating element; This means that the crimped section will run much cooler than the glowing element.</p>

<p>The charcoal colored circular element insulation, around the entire heating element is made from an extremely lightweight Corning ceramic structure. It is very brittle and easy to crumble&ndash;nearly impossible not to fracture as you try to move it even slightly. It reminds me of the material for the tiles on the space shuttle&ndash;but far less quality.</p>

<p>What you see below is the larger crimp part installed over top of the original and also crimped to the solid conductor at the entry point to the element assembly&hellip;</p>

<p><img src="/images-range/range-12_400x307.png" alt="heat element repaired with larger connector" /></p>

<p>Afterwards we did a full power test on the element. You can see that it is evenly heated with no noticable hot-spots at the mending point. The mended crimp point is relatively cool compared to the glowing element. It looks great and hopefully will last a long time.</p>

<p><img src="/images-range/range-13_400x232.png" alt="heat element full power on" /></p>

<p>On to the left-side element. It was much easier to find the breakpoint in this element. There was a visual burn mark where it had failed, again, right near the feed conductor at the edge of the heating element assembly.</p>

<p><img src="/images-range/range-14_400x267.png" alt="heat element front-left" /></p>

<p><img src="/images-range/range-15_400x267.png" alt="heat element shows fault at burn mark" /></p>

<p>This time, learning from the previous experience, I started with a larger crimping part which was fabicated from one of the larger parts in the crimping connector kit. I crimped the part using the larger needle-nose pliers again to make solid electrical contact.</p>

<p><img src="/images-range/range-16_400x206.png" alt="connector crimp" /></p>

<p><img src="/images-range/range-17_400x163.png" alt="connector bent open" /></p>

<p>Notice also that I removed the insulation ring temporarily to provides access towards the edge of the element.</p>

<p><img src="/images-range/range-18_400x267.png" alt="heat element repaired with connector crimped" /></p>

<p>After replacing the insulation ring and performing a successful full-power test, we begin to re-assemble the range.</p>

<p><img src="/images-range/range-19_400x267.png" alt="range top replacing screw" /></p>

<p><img src="/images-range/range-20_400x271.png" alt="range top opened" /></p>

<p><img src="/images-range/range-22_400x331.png" alt="range top closed" /></p>

<p>With wallet still in-tact and the range installed again into the kitchen; We use the repaired center element on the right-front to heat up lunch.</p>

<p><img src="/images-range/range-25_400x204.png" alt="range top pan with food being heated" /></p>

<p>&hellip;and celebrate success with a hot meal and a great tasting brew from Great Lakes brewery.</p>

<p><img src="/images-range/range-27_400x267.png" alt="lunchtime meal at table" /></p>

<h2>How much $ did we get paid ??</h2>

<p>There are lots of different ways to look at this. It helps to consider that by saving $320 and spending about an hour to complete the work, we got paid $320 per hour to fix the range. If we had a repair technician do the work it would have cost an additional $80 or so making it $400. Considering all, we might consider that <strong>we got paid $400 per hour cash (take home) to fix our own range, and we learned some new skills</strong>&ndash;what a deal! That&rsquo;s a big win.</p>

<h2>Update - This solution worked for only about 4 weeks!</h2>

<p>It has been 4 weeks and both of the repaired elements have failed again. In hindsight I probably should have chosen a better crimping material, such as a steel clip or short section of a small tight spring to hold the element together. The light gauge aluminum material crimp was probably going through too much thermal stress. Another approach might have been to spot-weld the element instead of using crimping part. A small Arc Stick Welder could be purchased for around $120. That would have probably done the trick.</p>

<h2>Time for a new range</h2>

<p>I decided to forgo further work on the older slide-in and ordered a new range. This time around we picked a slightly upper-model coil type from GE, model JBP35DDWW. I am impressed with this one. It has a much larger oven and some very serious heat capacity on the range-top. It costs less than half the price of the original Fridigair slide-in. The GE outperforms the Frigidair slide in by a long shot. The new unit has 2 3000 watt 8 inch coils on the range top. The direct coil contact heat elements transfer heat far better than the glass top on the earlier unit. The new coil range cooks far more quickly than the glass top range. If a burner goes out, it costs only $20 to $30 dollars to replace it. I will never buy a glass top range again&ndash;they are inferior over-priced junk!</p>

<p><img src="/images-range/new-range-ge-JBP35DDWW_400x402.png" alt="new GE range" /></p>

<h3>Disclaimer:</h3>

<p>The information provided here is not a suggestion or endorsement that anyone should attempt to perform the activities shown or described. This information is provided as-is to show how I solved the problem described. Any repairs you make are done at your own risk. The author assumes no responsibility or liability for the actions of others or the results obtained or problems encountered, including loss of any kind, from use of the information on this site.</p>

<p>In other words; You better know what you are doing before trying your own repair work. If you are unsure as to what you are doing, then seek out a qualified service technician to perform the work.</p>

<p>document date: 2013-04-21</p>

<p><a href='#TOP'><img alt="back to top of page" style="border-width:0" src="images/nav-to-top_80x23.png" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Auto Repair: Fixing the BMW 325 faulty rear tail light]]></title>
    <link href="http://runlevel-6.github.io/runlevel-6/blog/2013/04/04/auto-repair-fixing-the-bmw-325-faulty-rear-tail-light/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-04T23:49:08-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://runlevel-6.github.io/runlevel-6/blog/2013/04/04/auto-repair-fixing-the-bmw-325-faulty-rear-tail-light</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I am posting this information with hope that it might help others who are experiencing the same problem I am having with the E46 tail light assembly. If you find it of good use, please drop me an email to let me know. Please read the disclaimer at the bottom of this document.</p>

<p>Can you spot the problem in this rear tail light connector?</p>

<p><img src="/images-e46/show_bad_lead_400x300.jpg" alt="rear light assembly" /></p>

<h3>Forward</h3>

<p>My 18 year old son has been having problems with his 2001 BMW 325i. The body style is E46. The right tail light is not working properly. It is blinking too fast and does not seem to have enough illumination. It recently stopped working at all. I told him not to drive it until we had it repaired, so of course he has been quite anxious to get back to driving his car—he loves his BMW. He has been avoiding driving the “spare” family van, a rusty 94 Mercury Villager with a broken heater, broken AC, and 198,000 miles on it—can you blame him? Always up for a challenge and also for saving a buck or two, I decided to take a crack at fixing the BMW&hellip; :)</p>

<h3>Problem described:</h3>

<p>The right rear directional indicator, or turn signal, is very dim and flashes too quickly. Other lights within the same assembly are also very dim. The car keeps indicating a directional light warning on the dash panel. This problem went on for a couple of weeks and now, as of very recently, it has stopped working completely.</p>

<h3>Possible solutions:</h3>

<p>My first thought was that the problem might be with the light bulbs, so they were all checked and were found to be working perfectly. Next thought was that the problem could be a blown fuse. We checked the fuses, and they were ok as well. I started looking into replacement of the relay mechanism. The relay seems to be difficult to get to, so I went to the web for some information.</p>

<p>While searching around for information on the relay I was able to find out that there is a <a href="http://forum.e46fanatics.com/showthread.php?t=533309&amp;highlight=melted+tail+light">documented problem</a> in the way the light assembly has been designed for this car. Although I am grateful for the author&rsquo;s post on this, I believe this solution looks far more complicated than it needs to be. I solved it instead using one single wire connection back into the BMW 325i E46 wire harness.</p>

<p>The design problem appears to be in the material BMW chose for the ground return circuit in the tail light assembly, stamped steel sheathing. This material can not handle the ground return current. It basically gets too hot and eventually fries out at the thinnest point (least conductive) which happens to be within the connector contact area. I would not be suprised to find out that other BMW body styles have the same problem assuming that the folks at BMW might be using similar material selections on other vehicles.</p>

<h3>Problem solved:</h3>

<p>The solution I chose was to remove the ground return path from the connector and provide a much more conductive path using an external piece of 12 gauge stranded copper wire pulled from an old AC cord. Nothing beats copper wire for moving electrons. Ok, perhaps a super-conductor, but we aren&rsquo;t going there today :)</p>

<p>The repair job took me about 40 minutes or so to complete&ndash;it took me far longer to write this article. The lights on the vehicle are now working perfectly!</p>

<h3>Step by step what I did to solve the problem:</h3>

<p>Below is a view of the 2001 BMW 325i E46 rear light assembly, once it has been removed from the trunk area.</p>

<p><img src="/images-e46/e46_right_rear_light_assembly_400x300.jpg" alt="rear light assembly" /></p>

<p>Notice the burnt-out conductor below. The third conductor from the right of the connector. It has basically melted and corroded away from the intense heat. &ndash;very poor choice of material in this case—shame on BMW for that one.</p>

<p><img src="/images-e46/show_bad_lead_400x300.jpg" alt="rear light assembly" /></p>

<p>Below I have cut the bad conductor from the assembly using a pair of snub-nose wire clippers. You don&rsquo;t want to leave the old unattached conductor in the assembly, it could short out one of the other conductors if it came loose.</p>

<p><img src="/images-e46/cut_bad_lead_400x300.jpg" alt="rear light assembly" /></p>

<p>Below I have removed the bad conductor from the connector assembly. I just pull it out from the bottom using a pair of needle-nose pliers. Notice also that I have raised and clipped the strip at the thicker area to ready it for a new slide-on connector&hellip;</p>

<p><img src="/images-e46/removed_lead_400x300.jpg" alt="rear light assembly" /></p>

<p>You will need some tooling for performing electircal crimping. This is very inexepensive equipment and can be found at your local hardware, electrical, or builders supply store, such as Lowes or Home Depot. I just happen to have this stuff in my repair box for situations like this. Below is a picture of the tooling I used for this job. There is also DELL laptop with mouse in the picture, but you won&rsquo;t need either of those for this job. :)</p>

<p><img src="/images-e46/termination-kit_400x533.jpg" alt="rear light assembly" /></p>

<p>Below I have used the crimping tool and a blue slide-on connector to attached a new ground lead to the thicker, more conductive part of the metal strip. The unit is now ready to take back and install into the vehicle. If you do this you must make sure that the wire you pick is of greater current carrying capacity than what is found in the wiring harness in the car. In my case I used 12 gauge stranded copper wire which is a considerable improvement in conductivity than to what BMW is using in the wire harness. 14 gauge stranded copper would be great also. I would not go any smaller than 14 gauge. This piece of 12 gauge was cut and pulled from an old extension cord lying around the house.</p>

<p><img src="/images-e46/lead_attached_400x300.jpg" alt="rear light assembly" /></p>

<p>Now we are ready to install the light assembly unit back into the vehicle. Make sure all of the bulbs are inserted back into the assembly and take it back to the trunk of the vehicle.</p>

<p>Below is the unit sitting in the trunk and connected to the wire-harness. You&rsquo;ll have to excuse the visible junk in the trunk—my son is not very particular about his car trunk. As you can see, I have clipped the brown ground lead from the vehicle&rsquo;s wire harness and connected my green ground wire to it using another blue crimping connector from the connector set above. The crimp tooling and connectors are great to work with; Simple to use, effective, and quick!</p>

<p><img src="/images-e46/connection_complete_400x300.jpg" alt="rear light assembly" /></p>

<p>Next we snapped the light assembly back into position within the trunk and checked out the lights. Hooray! Everything is now working perfectly. Lights are as bright and snappy as the day the vehicle was purchased. The light warning is no longer appearing at the dash board. My son can now drive his car again! He&rsquo;s a happy camper and we are not out the $ hundreds it would have probably cost us to deal with the BMW service center.</p>

<p>&hellip;As a precautionary measure I checked the left rear light assembly for the same problem. The materials and connectors are the same on the left side, but I did not see any sign of a problem on that side. For now, I decided to leave the left side alone. Perhaps we&rsquo;ll be dealing with the left side in the future. :)</p>

<p>A few other things we have done at home with this BMW 325i E46 since we purchased it as a used vehicle a few years back:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Changed break shoes and brake wear sensors front and back—pretty easy task and saved us a bundle.</p></li>
<li><p>Performed regular oil and filter change.</p></li>
<li><p>Fixed a leaking O-ring on the top radiator hose.</p></li>
<li><p>Changed serpentine belt on front of the engine—that one was fun—NOT!</p></li>
<li><p>Front end alignment—yes we can do that also without the use of any expensive equipment!</p></li>
<li><p>Changed the rear drivers-side window drive motor.</p></li>
</ol>


<h3>Disclaimer:</h3>

<p>The information provided here is not a suggestion or endorsement that anyone should attempt to perform the activities shown or described. This information is provided as-is to show how I solved the problem described. Any repairs you make are done at your own risk. The author assumes no responsibility or liability for the actions of others or the results obtained or problems encountered, including loss of any kind, from use of the information on this site.</p>

<p>In other words; You better know what you are doing before trying your own repair work. If you are unsure as to what you are doing, then seek out a qualified mechanic to perform the work.</p>

<p><a href='#TOP'><img alt="back to top of page" style="border-width:0" src="images/nav-to-top_80x23.png" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Librecad: Creating a detailed design drawing for a basement remodel job.]]></title>
    <link href="http://runlevel-6.github.io/runlevel-6/blog/2013/03/05/librecad-basement-remodel/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-05T02:10:05-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://runlevel-6.github.io/runlevel-6/blog/2013/03/05/librecad-basement-remodel</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I am posting this information with hope that it might help others who are interested in improving their home and looking for a great way to document and move forward with a plan for home improvement. If you find this document useful, then please drop me an email to let me know. Please read the disclaimer at the bottom of this document. Update: Please note that <strong>LibreCAD was originally called QCAD</strong>.</p>

<p>Below is a basement home improvement design in LibreCAD</p>

<p><img src="/images-librecad/qcad_basement_plan_400x298.png" alt="qcad design graphic" /></p>

<h3>Forward</h3>

<p>We have been living in our home for several years now. Recently my wife and I have been talking about doing some improvements in the basement. We decided that finishing part of the basement would provide an increase in living space and also provide a great way to relax and spend time with our family and friends.</p>

<h3>Creating a Detailed Drawing</h3>

<p>By creating a detailed drawing we are able to discuss and consider more details and and to easily modify the plan while we make changes. The drawing is a very detailed model that allows you to visualize how the finished project will eventually look. It forces you to think about and deal with many of the details of the project before getting started with any materials. Once you create a scaled drawing can more easily plan for the obstacles and limitations that you have in the existing area. Things like floor drains, plumbing pipes, heating ducts, furnace, windows, hot water tank, electrical breaker box, and other details must be carefully worked into the plan.  A detailed drawing gives you confidence in what you are planning to do.</p>

<h3>Searching for a CAD software package:</h3>

<p>Some CAD software tools are very time consuming to learn. They can also be very expensive, running into the $thousands for a single user license. The first place I searched for a CAD package was in the package manager on my Ubuntu Linux system. I was looking for something that was easy to learn and provided enough power to get the job done. I found LibreCAD, an open source CAD package which is licensed under the GPL. What a gem this software package turned out to be. It is rock solid and provides all of the functionality I need to produce a quality scale drawing.</p>

<h3>Creating the design drawing:</h3>

<p>The first thing I did in LibreCAD was to set the default units of measurement and length for the drawing. I set units to inches and length to inches with a precision of 1/2”. You can work in just about any units and precision you&rsquo;d like of course. I then carefully documented where everything was in the basement. This involved measuring the foundation walls, identifying and drawing all of the ductwork, beams, support posts, plumbing fixtures, service interfaces for plumbing, water, and electrical fixtures. These items were grouped and placed in various layers of the drawing. I then added the improvements into the design, carefully working around everything that was already there. It took some time, but allowed me to think through many of the details that may have been missed without going through the drawing, or visual modeling, process.</p>

<h3>Screen shots of LibreCAD in action</h3>

<p>Below is LibreCAD up and running with the basement plan opened. You can see that I have created layers in the drawing which are identified in the rightmost pane. Each layer can be made visible or invisible in the drawing. Different line attributes can be assigned for each layer. Although the drawing looks complicated, it was actually quite easy to create after spending some time learning LibreCAD.</p>

<p><a href="images-librecad/qcad_basement_plan_1024x762.png" target="_blank"> <img src="http://runlevel-6.github.io/runlevel-6/images-librecad/qcad_basement_plan_400x298.png" border="0" alt="librecad detailed diagram" /></a></p>

<p>LibreCAD does a great job at exporting graphics to postscript format. You can easily view the output file in Adobe acrobat or an open source document viewer. It supports output to standard paper sizes including very large paper formats used for plotters. Below is an example of the same drawing in print preview ready to be exported to post script or printed directly.</p>

<p><a href="images-librecad/qcad_basement_plan_print_preview_1024x762.png" target="_blank"> <img src="http://runlevel-6.github.io/runlevel-6/images-librecad/qcad_basement_plan_print_preview_400x298.png" border="0" alt="librecad print diagram" /></a></p>

<h3>An example librecad design file</h3>

<p>If you would like an example copy of a LibreCAD .dxf basement plan, you can download it from my website here: <A HREF="/download/basement_plan.dxf">basement_plan.dxf</A></p>

<p>Once you spend some time with LibreCAD I think you will agree; This is a great tool to have for home improvement planning. It also works great for other 2D CAD applications, such as in designing mechanical parts for fabrication. I have also used it for design work on some woodworking projects.</p>

<p><a href='#TOP'><img alt="back to top of page" style="border-width:0" src="http://runlevel-6.github.io/runlevel-6/images/nav-to-top_80x23.png" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
